this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software developers are you ready it's
time to upgrade your data platform to
inner systems iris choose your language
choose your tools choose your
environment collaborate build faster and
deploy more efficiently when you can
make faster decisions there's no telling
what you'll create ready set code start
coding for free visit inner systems comm
slash try to try iris
hello this is Justin buyer for software
engineering radio and today I'm speaking
with torn sandal torn is the co-creator
of the open policy agent OPA project and
the VP of open source at steer the
company rethinking authorization for
cloud native systems at Sierra Turin
leads development of the OPA project and
focuses on helping users and partners
succeed torn is a frequent speaker on
policy and authorization at conferences
like cube con os con velocity and more
join give the audience a quick
introduction to what a policy engine is
sure so a policy engine is you can kind
of think of it in layman's terms is kind
of like a concierge for your service so
it kind of exists to like offload policy
decisions from your software from your
applications from your API gateways from
your you know your orchestrators from
scripts and see ICD pipelines to SSH
Damon's and so on so a policy and Jen
kind of exists to answer questions for
your software when your software needs
to make some kind of decision and has a
question to ask okay so essentially it's
trying to offload some of the
decision-making out of your application
core and instead allow you to express
decision making process in a separate
instance yeah and and it can be you know
it can be in a library or it can be in a
separate process that runs on the same
machine or it can be in a separate
container that's in the same pod or it
can be you know in a service that's
running across the network
but generally the idea behind policy
engines is they they kind of exist to
decouple policy enforcement from policy
decision-making so the decision-making
that gets handled by the policy engine
based on rules and logic that have been
fed into it and then the enforcement
resides inside of the software that
queries it so you know if you're
building like an application now that
had to serve a REST API then you know
every time that REST API gets gets
queried it's gonna have to decide
whether or not to allow that that API
request and so the way that that
typically would work with the policy
engine is that whatever the API request
comes in the application would query the
policy engine and say should this API
request be allowed and the the policy
engine will do a bunch of crunching and
figure out you know essentially yes or
no whether that should happen it'll hand
that answer back to the service or to
the application so that it can be
enforced okay so essentially it'll make
a boolean logic decision and return that
to the application
and just a table we will definitely go
back and talk a little bit more about
the implementation of a policy engine in
an application but I just want to change
direction a little bit and start
specifically talking about the project
you're involved in open policy Asia so
what is it how does it fit into this
domain of policy engines sure so so the
open policy agent or OPA as we like to
call it some people call it OPA
we call it OPA people can call it
whatever they want we like to call it
OPA we started the project a while ago
about four years ago and in early 2016
and what what OPA which kind of provides
is this is basically a building block
for enforcing policies consistently
across a wide range of software so at
its core it provides a way to express
policy and then an engine to evaluate
policies and produce decisions that can
then be handed back to your software to
be enforced okay that makes sense so how
specifically does ople work so the way
the way that OPA works is that you you
express your policies in a high-level
declarative language that's kind of
purpose-built for expressing policies
and rules and then you feed those rules
into OPA via well-defined api's or off
of the file system or or however you
want and then whenever your software
needs to make a decision or needs to
obtain a decision it can query OPA and
it can ask you know give me back the
decision for these for these inputs so
for example if you were building a micro
service and that service exposed an API
to serve you know financial reports or
something like that or salary
information and whenever you know a
request comes in to your service to to
look up the salary of an employee or to
look up some you know financial report
the service would decide to quit we need
to make a decision about that and it
would query OPA and inside of that query
would describe the request that was
happening unto itself right so it would
provide things like the method and the
URL and the HTTP headers and maybe even
the message body and all this data I
mean it would give that over to OPA and
it would be asking basically for a
decision a yes or no like a boolean
answer like true or false and so then
open would evaluate the rules that you
would had been fed to it previously and
it would out the outcome of that
evaluation process would be the decision
it would be true or false or allowed an
IR
you want to say and that would be set
back your service to be enforced okay so
essentially I take a policy I write it
in this high-level language and then I
put it into OPA through whatever method
it be and then my application then uses
OPA to say based on this information
that I received should I allow this
request or deny this request exactly so
there's kind of like two sides to it
there's the there's there's you as a
policy author and somebody who's
responsible for kind of managing policy
in the system right so you're
responsible for writing down the rules
that govern who can do what and maybe
you're also responsible for building out
some of the systems that distribute
those rules and then there's the
software that actually needs to get
decisions when things are happening when
API requests are coming in when users
are trying to SSH into machines you know
when scripts are running inside of CIC
pipelines that software is is solely
concerned with the decision like getting
back a decision from OPA and so it'll
it'll ask open for policy decisions when
it needs them okay and how do you
express this policy what's the language
for it so the language for expressing
policy with OPA is called Rago and Rago
is is it's a latin word it means to rule
so we thought that was a good good name
for a policy language it turned out that
we didn't have any Australians on the
core team and it turned out that that
Rago actually mean a rage Oh is it's
pronounced mean it's car registration in
Australia so we we learned that a little
bit too late to kind of rename it but so
anyway you're right you're right
nonetheless you write your rules and
ray-ray go and and what they what they
basically exist to do is answer
questions right because your software's
got to make these decisions and those
decisions are often formed in terms of
questions right like is you know Alice
allowed to see you know Bob salary or
something like that right is this
workload allowed to be deployed or you
know more interesting like what what
policies could be violated if this
workload were to be employed or what
records you know should someone be
allowed to see right these are these are
all kind of questions that our policy in
nature all right so the language that
the dopa gives you is a high-level
declarative language that lets you write
down rules that govern those kinds of
decisions and so the language is is very
good at expressing kind of just kind of
logical statements over arbitrary sets
of data okay so it's essentially
implementing
actually based authentication or
authorization to that extent so it's
saying here's this attribute and my
policy is that Jane can see financial
data but you can't see personnel records
so I would write that in Ray go and say
users with this attribute of financial
manager can see financial records but
can't see personnel records yeah exactly
there's typically like a phase before
authorization which is authentication
that happens you know before before you
actually decide whether or not to allow
or deny some kind of request and so that
that authentication phase is super
important but once that finishes like
once you've kind of decide or proven
verified that you know Alice is who she
says she is then you need to make this
decision and that that that
decision-making process comes down to
comes down to logic and it comes down to
attributes that describe who Alice is
what action she's trying to perform what
resource she's trying to access as well
as the environment that all the software
is running in right it might depend on
what device Alice is connecting from it
might depend on how she authenticated
did she do go through multi-factor or
not they like depend on you know the
time of day and so on right there's all
kinds of different environmental factors
that affect the the decision making
process and so with OPA and Ray go what
we try to do is give people a language
that's very good at at expressing logic
over all these kinds of these kinds of
attributes okay so I would authenticate
the user and let's say give them back
and oo auth token with the attributes
about how they authenticated whether
they used multi-factor and then when
they come back to the application
provide that token to prove that's they
are who they say they are
that's where OPA fits in and starts to
apply the policies almost and we will
touch on this little bit later in that
zero trust networking kind of way yeah
exactly so so typically the way the Wii
the Wii the way that we think about I'd
like identity and you know token like oh
aw tokens or JSON web tokens is that
they are just another kind of set of
attributes that inform the decision
making process there's nothing
inherently special about I mean they're
they're obviously super fundamental to
the to the policy but you know there are
lots of other things that are important
so they're just another source of data
or context that informs the decision
making process so that's kind of how it
works at a high level you know when you
actually start writing Rago what you're
essentially doing is putting down just a
bunch of if-then statements you say you
know a lot you are allowed to perform
this operation under these conditions
and you kind of just write down the
conditions under which things are
allowed to happen or not allowed to
happen or you know potentially how you
know the incoming requests may need to
be modified or changed or obligations
that might fall on the client and so on
okay so changing direction a little bit
here let's talk about how it's actually
implemented so I take OPA and I have my
application that exists what kinds of
applications benefit from me putting
open and are we talking you know small
applications huge enterprise
applications large distributed systems
where does that benefit start to show
with OPA so we made a very conscious
decision early on in the project to try
to keep it as as kind of flexible and
domain agnostic and general purpose as
possible and so I personally think that
applications big and small in different
kinds of domains can actually can
actually benefit quite a bit from it
where we see a lot of interest to today
for the project is from companies
enterprises large organizations that it
operate in you know highly regulated
environments like financial services
companies you know healthcare companies
and so on and and we see kind of like
two broad categories of use cases so one
use case is mostly around configuration
validation essentially this is what
people are typically talking about when
they when they talk about open the
context of kubernetes in that context
OPA kind of exists to put safeguards or
guardrails in place that protect the
clusters the communities clusters as
well as the like the applications that
are running on top of those clusters
from from themselves and from it from
each other and so on so that's kind of
like one broad category of use cases
just kind of safeguarding platform
configuration and and you know the the
metadata that defines compute network
and storage resources in the sort of
cloud native stack the second kind of
major category of a use case or kind of
application for OPA is is just this kind
of
i authorized a ssin problem right every
single time you build a micro service or
some sort of application you you have to
build out triple a right authentication
authorization and accounting and so
there are kind of industry standard ways
of doing authentication and butbut
authorization on the other hand is
typically been deeply kind of embedded
into the end of the business logic and
what we're seeing now is that people are
kind of realizing that it's better to
decouple that and split it out and
offload it to a component like OPA so
there are all kinds of api authorization
use cases around micro services as well
as applications whether you're talking
about role like implementing role based
access control or you know attribute
based access control or you want to
implement you know an AWS IAM style
access control model there are various
companies that are using open just
exactly for that ok so one of the huge
benefits is almost I can have a
consistent authorization across my
entire stack so if I put up a kubernetes
cluster and launch my new application
and I'm already using OPA as the basis
of authorization for my existing 400
applications I can then take those same
roles and apply specific controls within
that application but still map to those
same roles yeah there's nothing there's
nothing kind of that we didn't hit you
from from load from using contextual
information that describes like the
running software when you're writing
policy for kubernetes clusters or
running policy for your for your
services and having the ability to you
know express policy in a kind of a
uniform and consistent way across a wide
range of software whether you're talking
about you know micro services or
platform services or you know even even
host level Damons like SSH is
tremendously valuable when you're
talking about these large organizations
that otherwise have very poor kind of
control and visibility over the rules
the governance of the system exactly so
there's definitely some compliance
benefits that you could get out of it
which I'm gonna circle back a little bit
later to talk on some of those benefits
but just to dive a little bit deeper
into the OPA client and how that would
be implemented how does it handle a lot
of the issues we see with like
distributed systems where you know we
can't get a hundred percent network
reliability or you might end up with a
split brain problem or something to that
effect sure that's a good question so
when
when it actually comes to you know using
oppa to integrating it into your into
your stack or your software you have a
you have a couple different options and
we kind of tend to think of oppa as this
essentially like this host local cash
for policy decision-making so you can
either embed it as a library if your
building services and go or you can
actually just run it as a daemon as a
standalone server but in either case
well I mean in in both cases we
recommend that you run it essentially as
close to your software as possible right
so if it's embedded as a library it's
it's in the same process but if it's
running as a daemon we recommend you
take it and you run it as a host level
daemon essentially next to your next
year software or in the case of
kubernetes as a sidecar container that's
a sort of an architectural pattern
within kubernetes and the the reason
that we recommend that you do that yeah
is sort of twofold right so if if you
imagine like an application that's
that's kind of designed with a
service-oriented or Microsoft's
architecture when an incoming request
hits that application it might have to
traverse you know four or five or ten or
you know a dozen or twenty or something
micro services in order for it to be
fulfilled and if at every single hop
along the way your services or your
software has to call out across the
network to get a policy decision back
then there are a few different things
that can go wrong and I think you kind
of alluded to them there a little bit
with things like split-brain right so
one one thing that can happen is that
you know the network can get slow or it
can it'll injury it's certainly going to
introduce latency into into the path
right and so if they're every hop you
have to pay this network overhead then
that's going to impact your your overall
application latency right and so your
your application is not going to perform
as well and your users are gonna be you
know unhappy the other impact is that
it's gonna affect your applications
uptime it's gonna affect its
availability because if at every single
hop along the way you have to call it
across the network then if there's a
network partition or the host that open
is running on crashes it dies then your
application is not gonna be able to get
a decision back right it's gonna it's
gonna the service is gonna ask over for
decision and it's just gonna sit there
waiting until sometime ode expires and
then it's gonna it's gonna fail it's
gonna encounter an error and it's gonna
have to make a decision that guess
basically at that point about what to do
because authorization is kind of this
this fundamental security problem
because it exists in the critical path
of your application you typically have
to fail closed so that's going to impact
your availability it's gonna impact your
your uptime and so because of that
because of performance and availability
we recommend that you take open and you
run it as close to your software as
possible ideally on the on the same
machine okay so it's the classic
balancing security and you know the
confidentially confidentiality integrity
and availability you know balancing
those all out and by putting it as close
as possible to the service we're still
getting the availability that we
probably need for our service but still
ensuring we get the required security
controls in place for our application
especially if it's something in a highly
regulated industry where the expectation
is every request should be authorized to
some extent before it's allowed yeah now
of course OPA is very flexible you can
embed it as a library you can stand it
up as a daemon if you want to run it
across the network if you want to run it
as a service we don't stop you you can
do that but it is it is kind of on you
to think about the availability and
performance impact that's gonna incur on
your application so you know we don't we
don't try to we don't force you to run
it on every machine or next every
application but that's that's kind of
our that's that's that's how we thought
about it but beginning was that it would
enable a distributed enforcement model
for policy and authorization right it
didn't a lot of legacy systems will are
kind of overly centralized you know they
were designed for like a like older
environments and so that's one of the
things that open does a little bit
differently okay and that definitely is
helpful to know that it's able to handle
this distributed systems issue but just
a little bit more on that as we're
talking about putting open as almost a
sidecar to every application or as close
as possible to the application how do I
manage all of these OPA agents and
provide a consistent policy across all
of them right yeah so if you have like
all of these these agents that are there
and by the way OPA keeps all of the
rules and data that it uses to make
decisions in memory so it doesn't have
any kind of like decision time
dependencies on any kind of external
database or anything like that right so
all the all the evaluation happens
locally inside of the agent there are
mechanisms to call out from inside of
the policy if you need to but by default
it doesn't it doesn't do that and if you
architect your policies the way that we
of encouraged than it will but so if you
if you have your have your kind of
architecture set up so you better these
agents running throughout your
infrastructure they're all storing
everything in memory you need some way
to manage them right you need some way
to kind of control what policies and
rules they have loaded and you want to
know you want to know you know what
decisions they're making at the end of
the day right that's important for audit
and accounting and so what OPA does to
enable that is it exposes a set of
management api's so those api's are
basically they just exist to provide
control and visibility over the agents
so OPA has an API called the bundle API
which you can use to essentially
distribute bundles of policy and data
out to the agents essentially you
configure OPA to periodically phone home
to a remote HTTP server and Oakland will
kind of sit there trying to get the
latest version of policy and it'll it'll
periodically download it and activate it
and so that can be a simple HTTP server
you know serving off of a file system
you can point open at s3 you can write
you know your own service to serve
policy and data and we see people doing
all kinds of stuff like that
OPA also has other API is for visibility
so it's got a we call status API for
receiving notifications about basically
like what version of policy OPA is
currently running and whether they're
running issues activating the last the
last version that it got from your from
your bundle API and then there's also
this the decision log API so that you
can configure open to keep a little
record in memory every time it makes a
decision so every time your software
queries OPA it'll keep a record of that
around I mean that record includes all
of the input attributes and the decision
that was made as well as a pointer to
the version of the policy that it had
loaded when it made the decision and
then it'll periodically flush those out
it'll upload those to remote API or
it'll send them to a logger and so then
you can kind of aggregate those
decisions and do all kinds of analysis
on them so OPA has these kind of like
primitive api's they that architects and
developers can can kind of build on top
of if they want and then there of course
there are companies like styro --that
provide a commercial control plan for
managing policy agent deployments ok so
the policy agent itself is almost a data
plane level agent providing
the authorization for a service and then
you would still want a control plane to
provide the policy gather feedback from
the agent check statuses verify it's
running the latest policy so that you
can detect issues like an agent running
one version of policy and then you push
out a critical change because you notice
an issue with it that way you can detect
well these agents over here in this
application aren't being updated why
exactly yeah having having like this
visibility understanding the performance
and and you know state excuse me of the
opus is super important and then also
having a kind of a record of the
decisions that the agents have been
making is also super valuable from an
audit perspective because now you can
kind of build up this historical record
of all the decisions that have been made
over time you know across your cross
your your stack effectively so that's
powerful for audit it kind of feeds back
into into rollout and distribution of
policy because you can use that
historical record to do things like back
testing and and and so on policy changes
before you go and roll them out calling
all developers there's no telling what
you can create when you upgrade your
data platform to inner systems iris are
you ready to build the applications you
want however you want them are you ready
to develop applications faster than ever
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today enter systems iris
data platform ready set code start
coding for free visit inner systems comm
/ try to try iris so tweren't when we're
talking about using OPA let's just focus
in a little bit more on the security
aspects of it where would we put OPA
into the application security stack I
know we're using it for authorization
and I know it's next to it your
application that you're running but
what's the advantage of using OPA over I
think very traditionally like an LDAP
query based on a security group or just
trying to take oh oh off claims and
enforce that in the application sure so
whenever whatever you're trying to
secure an application you know the first
thing you have to figure out is how
you're going to do identity and
authentication how you're going to
verify you know that I am who I say I am
when I'm connecting to the system and
that's what things like a loss kind of
you do right so off the way that I think
about OAuth is that it's sort of like
power of attorney for for software for
applications right it allows me to grant
some piece of software the ability to do
something on my my behalf
right but what Oh F doesn't define what
it doesn't solve for you is once once
that kind of grant has been made that
grant still has to be validated by the
server that's receiving the request from
the application right and so today and
in the past what happened is that the
validation of those grants those claims
would just be deeply embedded hard-coded
into the application business logic and
and that's for good reason because oh oh
if you go read the RF the OAuth RFC it
doesn't tell you you know this is how
the claims need to be validated it might
say for some of them what to do but for
others it says this is outside the scope
right it's just not part of oh so the
decision making around validation of
claims and stuff is an authorization
problem and it's a policy problem at the
end of the day so that's kind of where
OPA comes in what Opel allows you to do
is have that basic kind of claim
validation just simply offloaded from
the application right from the service
to a dedicated engine that allows you to
express it uniformly consistently across
a wide range of software and so this is
particularly valuable if you're talking
about you know a large organization
that's trying to roll out you know Oh
awesome you know so sort of
authentication practice like the
multi-factor across a wide range of
applications because instead of having
to go into each and every application
and we don't reconfigure it or make
changes to the implementation of that
application so that it supports
multi-factor they can just do that in
one place they can go into the policy
and they can say okay now require
multi-factor for you know users that are
connecting from you know certain
geographic regions or users that are
connecting to the system outside of
business hours or something like that
right it makes it much much easier to
roll out these kind of like enterprise
or organization wide security policies
to fleets of applications okay that
makes sense so it gives you that generic
container where you can tell the generic
container of ooofff hey based on these
claims this is how I interpret these and
then within the application be able to
query that consistently and say I got
these claims
what do I do or is this action
acceptable exactly and there are
different ways you can do that
integration it can happen inside of the
application itself the application can
query Oppo and say is this token valid
but it can it can also happen elsewhere
it could happen inside of the the kind
of app or web framework that the
applications implement inside of right
so take like a spring you know framework
for example right you can just have a
simple spring security plug-in that
knows how to query OPA whenever an
incoming request comes in you can also
do it outside of the application with
the service proxy like envoy right so
that's that's another way of integrating
is to just have or rather inserting
policy enforcement of your stack is to
take a proxy like envoy put it in front
of your application and then configure
envoy to talk to OPA and ask for for
example oh you know tokens to be
validated as a request to come into the
system okay so it's still is able to
pull that you know authorization out of
the application and it's really just
focused on doing that within OPA now
changing gears just a little bit here we
did do an episode on zero trust
networking episode 385 and I'll refer
viewers back to that for more
information on that field specifically
if they're not familiar but where does
OPA fit into that whole architecture of
zero trust networking so so zero trust
is kind of about you know removing
assumptions around security from the
system right so you know if you if you
look at you know legacies are like older
systems you know what they rely on is
kind of centralized perimeter base
network security right so it's kind of
like if you have a house and you put a
lock on on the front door right that
that's kind of like perimeter based
security right inside of the house
there's no locks you can go into any
room at any time and and it's it's kind
of free free for all with zero trust
you're basically going into the house
and putting locks on every single door
now that could be a little bit kind of
creepy I guess but but the but the idea
is kind of it's kind of sound right and
so the challenge there I think a lot of
the time is around you know usability
right how do you how do you kind of
maintain usability and how do you kind
of make security something that doesn't
just totally get in people's way because
otherwise they'll find ways to bypass I
can get around it but but OPA is kind of
like this engine that you can use to put
locks on every single door
in your house it's it's intended to be
super lightweight and super easy to to
embed so it does fit very nicely into
these kind of like zero trust
architectures and with oppa can we
leverage I know you mentioned enriching
the data but can we do a more like
complex authorization workflow like
saying if I logged in and wanted to do
this action now I need to be I can log
into the application without
multi-factor but now that I want to do
an admin action I need to do
multi-factor yeah that's a that's a good
question and I think earlier on when we
were talking we were focusing on
policies that generate kind of boolean
like decisions right like yes/no but one
of the things that kind of separates
open from a lot of other projects in the
past is that it actually allows you to
generate non boolean decisions the
decisions that you generate from your
OPA policies can actually be arbitrary
JSON documents JSON objects or values
and so what that means is that if you
want to generate a decision that says
well maybe you're allowed er no you're
not allowed but if you go off and you go
to this URL and you authenticate you
come back then then then you'll be
allowed access you that's something you
can actually express they quite easily
inside of inside of / ok so I still I
can provide a more complex workflow and
say oh well now that you want to do this
you have to go here or give back the
application more information other than
just a yes allow or no don't allow I can
say well I'm not sure they need to go
here and then come back and ask me again
exactly so we see this a lot with our
with our envoy integration people will
write policies that return the actual
HTTP headers that force a redirect of
clients coming into the system right so
it just builds on top of you know
standard HTTP you know redirection and
then can you give me a specific example
of an application where you've
implemented OPA and it improved the
security the application overall sure I
mean there are tons of companies that
have talked publicly about how they're
how they're using OPA at scale recently
we were we held our first-ever at OPA
summit back in San Diego at coop Con in
November and at that event we had a
bunch of different companies from kind
of different verticals come and talk
about how they're using OPA and one of
the coolest ones was how Pinterest is
actually leveraging OPA to enforce all
kinds of different policies across there
their system so they're using over for
standard stuff like config validation
inside of CI CD pipelines and they've
also they also talked about how they're
you know using it for api authorization
and micro services but then they're also
going even further and they're using it
to control access to Kafka right and so
Kafka is it's kind of like this this
data it is the data plan right for a lot
of organizations it has you know just a
huge amount of information flowing
through it on a daily basis right and so
they shared how they actually use open
at scale to enforce authorization or
access control over who can basically
connect to a certain kafka topics and
produce or read from them and the
numbers that they shared were pretty
impressive it was like at peak it was
serving about across their kafka fleet
it was serving something like 500
thousand authorization queries per
second globally across all of their
clusters and then when they added
caching on top of that it went up to
something like 8.5 million so the
numbers that they showed there were
pretty cool and it we just need to see
that that kind of publication of how
people are using OPIC I'll to solve real
security issues another another example
that came out from coop con was some
folks from Goldman Sachs that run
kubernetes showed how they use OPA to
not only define admission control
policies to safeguard the cluster to say
things like you know you're not allowed
to run privilege containers or you're
not allowed to run images off the public
Internet but they also use OPA to define
desired State or configuration for
kubernetes so like whenever a namespace
gets created right and this happens all
the time for new teams it's in
kubernetes policies are put in are in
place to automatically print so that so
that what happens is that automatically
security resources get provisioned so
things like our back roles things like
quota as well as other things like
persistent volumes and other objects so
there are tons of different different
use cases and I recommend that people go
online and kind of look around on
YouTube and other places for examples of
how people are running open in the wild
ok so essentially OPA has this huge
range of resources and we can use it for
things like authorization or we can go
all the way over almost on the other
side and say we're doing config
validation and we're almost forcing
baseline templates whenever you do any
type of specific action that's right
yeah and that's kind of been the goal
since the very beginning was to provide
a kind of a unified or a
assistant way to do that across a range
of software so it's been super
satisfying to see people actually get to
that point today so just changing gears
a little bit here I want to move over to
the compliance and audit side of it
how does using OPA help with that does
it help reduce how much work we have to
do when we're doing an audit of an
environment to verify that you know
appropriate access control is being
implemented I talked to someone a while
ago for a particular company and they
they told me about how they they tried
to embark on this exercise to determine
whether or not a public API request I
get a public request coming in from the
internet could access credit card data
basically in their in their in their
system and this was like a large-scale
application consisting of many micro
services or different kind of you know
layers layers of services and they
basically determined that it was gonna
be impossible to answer that because of
the fact that the authorization
decision-making was basically hard-coded
in you know in different places and
there was no way they were going to be
able to in an automated manner or even
in a manual manner go through and kind
of audit and figure out you know for
every different application or service
whether that was weather you know public
traffic could reach credit card data and
so the the value there for them for
using something like OPA
is that you no longer have to go into
each and every service right you no
longer have to go into each every
application and look at each and every
implementation of policy and
authorization right if you're a security
engineer or a compliance officer sound
like that in a large organization
there's no way you're gonna put a ramp
up on all of the different programming
languages and frameworks and you know
implementation patterns that that all
these different applications and
services are implemented with right and
so just having that that one you know
unified way of expressing policy across
a wide range of services I'm just just
by having that that kind of allows you
to decouple the decision-making from the
application business logic and have it
represented in one way that's that's
tremendously valuable if you talk to
people that do audits and so on from
from large organizations and highly
regulated industries they'll just
they'll tell you that Horror Story is
about spending weeks and weeks and weeks
inside of instead of meeting rooms
trying to try to do these these audits
and it's just it's very difficult
because there's so many different ways
of specifying who can do what and that's
what we're trying to solve exactly so
because
everybody's implementation is a little
bit different in every language is a
little bit different the way I might
implement authorization in one service
isn't necessarily the way I would
implement another and I might have five
hundred different patterns in one
service four hundred and another 200 and
this one over here and there's no way
you're ever gonna be able to trace down
all of those paths individually to say
well the requests that it's this service
than this service in this service will
never be able to get here unless it has
this attribute
whereas with up I can say oh here's this
general policy does it meet these
requirements and does the application
implement OPA correctly and if it does
then I can assume that it will be
enforced correctly exactly makes sense
so just going a little bit more into the
compliance side is there any benefit on
the like data governance side of the
stack so when we're talking about config
validation is there a way for me to say
my us customer data won't ever get
started in the kubernetes cluster we
have in Europe we do have some users
that are using open today for putting
putting access control basically in
place over self-service provisioning
platforms right so you know a lot of
organizations are trying to move towards
more kind of like self-service platforms
for provisioning things like message
brokers and databases along with
applications and that's great because it
kind of increases velocity for
developers and applications in the
organization but at the same time you
need to be careful right you don't want
to accidentally have you know someone's
data from from the EU getting getting
shipped off somewhere else right and so
putting putting kind of governance or
guardrails in place over over
self-service provisioning platforms is
is something that we see people using
OPA for today we also see people using
OPA to implement access control with
different data Lake kind of projects
right so Kafka is one example we've also
got integrations with things like SEF
and Mineo to implement similar types of
fine-grained authorization policies that
say you know you're only allowed to
connect to or you're only allowed to
access this bucket or these objects you
know if you're connecting from the right
geographic region at a certain point in
time you know and so on so the
authorization problem there is is quite
similar with
some were kind of speculative
integrations with oppa that they try to
go even further into the data
authorization problem and control access
to data at a very fine grained level so
like at the row level or at the column
level inside of a database and you can
do that today but it's definitely more
of a cutting-edge use case okay so more
of the cutting-edge ease case I could
put in oppa and say my column of credit
card numbers is inaccessible unless you
have the appropriate role to access a
full credit card number and I'm doing
that because I need it for PCI
compliance and now I can say with oppa
yes here's my policy that says that only
these people can access full primary
account number therefore I'm PCI
compliant cuz I'm limiting access to it
yeah and I mean it can go even further
than an app - and you could you might
want to say for example that you know a
customer like so suppose you're a large
you know financials firm and you've got
customer service agents you might not
ever want them to see like a social
security number for example right but
you'd want to allow people obviously to
see the last four digits of their own
social security numbers and then there
are certain people in the organization
like somebody from like risk or
something like that they need to be able
to see the full social security number
right and so the decision about like how
many digits to mask out on a social
security number is is another example of
a policy decision and it's another
that's an actual usage that some folks
have for open today okay so instead of
trying to implement that in my
application and then having six
applications that access the same
database I'll mask it a little bit
differently I have one system that's
saying if their customer service agent
they get no unmasked digits if they're
in fraud they get the last four if their
customer they get the last four and if
you're in finance you get the whole
thing exactly yeah awesome so that gives
me that ability then to almost make that
attestation and very cleanly provide one
single sheet of paper to my auditor and
say here's who has access to this
because these are the roles that they
have and this is the policy we enforce
exactly
yeah awesome and then is there anything
that I missed that you think a software
engineer should know no I think this was
this was super fun you know the project
is growing quite a bit we've got coop
con Europe event happening in at the end
of March the CNC F Linux donation event
happening at inner March
and lots of people are gonna be there
talking about Oprah policy agent so if
you're if you're in Europe at that time
definitely check it out
we love contributions back to the open
policy agents so if you are using it and
you have an idea or you know you see a
bug and you want to see it fixed you
know please come and engage with us and
we also love new integrations so if you
have ideas for free integrations for the
project with new pieces of software
please come and come and share that with
us one of the things we launched
recently was a was an ecosystem or
integration index on the website so if
you go to the website now you can see a
nice list of all the different
integrations that we know about and you
can submit a PR and your integration
will get added to that page so do check
that out that's awesome I'll definitely
make sure to include that link in the
show notes and then just one other thing
before we finish up I noticed a project
that seems similar to open policy agent
the gatekeeper project what is that
so gate keeper is part of open policy
agent what gatekeeper is is sort of like
an evolution of something that people
have been using OPA for for a long time
instead of kubernetes this problem of
admission control what we've done is
we've taken gatekeeper or sorry we've
taken OPA and we've kind of provided
some first-class integration with with
kubernetes so that project is being
developed jointly by styro Microsoft
Google and others and the kind of
mission there is to provide a
first-class you know kubernetes native
way of managing admission control policy
so it gives you some nice features on
top of OPA like like audit for example
leave the ability to audit your cluster
against your OPA policies and it also
introduces a kind of a way of
parameterizing or template izing your
europa policies that you can have kind
of packs or predefined sets of libraries
of policies that you can then easily
install in your cluster and then
configure and be off and running so
that's a super cool project it you know
represents the work of a lot of people
that's awesome and then what's the
future direction you see with OPA any
major changes on the horizon the the
project itself is pretty stable probably
gonna declare it like a one daughter
release pretty soon you know we take
things like backwards compatibility very
seriously and I think that oppa's doing
a pretty good job with its kind of like
core objective of enabling people to do
config validation and you know API
authorizations but there are some kind
of new use cases that are that are more
speculative like data filtering and I
mentioned the minute ago and data
masking they were they were trying to
improve they were kind of working on
improved support for and then we're also
one of the things we announced late last
year was kind of basic G aid support for
taking your opal policies and compiling
them into web assembly using OPA and so
that ability to target web assembly
runtimes
whether they're in a CDN or they're in a
service proxy or they're in a database
or they're in your browser is something
that's gonna be super powerful and is
gonna become more and more prevalent I
think so that's that's sort of on the
cutting edge of open development right
now well that'll be a fantastic product
to see coming out of OPA so torn I just
want to thank you for coming on the show
and discussing how we can leverage
policy engines like open policy agent
for software security this is Justin
buyer for software engineering radio
thank you for listening developers take
your marks it's time to upgrade your
data platform to inner systems iris it's
time to deliver complex mission-critical
applications in the fastest route
possible it's time to use any data from
any source it's time to embed analytics
and create interactive user interfaces
so what are you waiting for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner systems iris data platform the
fastest way to build applications ready
set code start coding for free visit
inner systems comm slash try to try iris
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening